# Sultan Mahmud Sajal

Sxs2561@psu.edu

smsajal.github.io

+1-814-380-3595

#### Research Interests

My research focuses on workload analysis and performance evaluation of Cloud Computing Systems. I am especially interested in faithfully scaling, analysing and synthesizing cloud workloads to facilitate realistic experimentation in both academia and industry. Much of my research has explored how different characteristics of the workload affect the performance of the system under different conditions and how we can modify the workload to our need while preserving important characteristics.

## **Education**

Expected 2023

Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering, The Pennsylvania State University Advisors: Dr. Timothy Zhu and Dr. Bhuvan Urgaonkar Selected Courses: Operating Systems Design, Performance Evaluation, Topics in Cloud Computing, Data Mining, Algorithm Design and Analysis, Computer Networks, Programming Language, Natural Language Processing, Database Systems

2013 - 2017

B.Sc. in Computer Science and Engineering, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology

Thesis topic: An Empirical Study on the Growth of New Languages and Their Users in Stack Overflow

**Advisor:** *Dr. Rifat Shahriyar* 

Selected Courses: Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, Operating System, Com-

puter Networks, Database.

#### **Publications**

- Sajal, Sultan Mahmud\* and Hasan\*, Rubaba, Zhu, T., Urgaonkar, B., & Sen, S. (2021). TraceSplitter: a **new paradigm for downscaling traces** [\*Equal Contribution]. Proceedings of the Sixteenth European Conference on Computer Systems, (EuroSys '21), 606–619.
- Sajal, Sultan Mahmud, Mehrab, Z., Zaman, I., Uddin, M., & Rahman, A. (2017). Poster Abstract: Handwriting Recognition Using Accelerometer. International Conference on Networking Systems and Security, (NSysS).

## Research Experience

2023 - Ongoing

- Facilitating Usage of Background Traffic for Realistic Experimentation in Cloud Systems
  - Mentors: Timothy Zhu and Bhuvan Urgaonkar (The Pennsylvania State University), Siddhartha Sen (Microsoft Research)
  - Motivate the need for collecting and using background trace with foreground trace
  - Develop efficient methods of replaying background trace in conjuction with foreground trace for realistic experimentation

## Research Experience (continued)

2020 - Ongoing

# ■ Upscale Workloads from Cloud Infrastructure and Large Datacenters

- Mentors: *Timothy Zhu* and *Bhuvan Urgaonkar* (The Pennsylvania State University), *Siddhartha Sen* (Microsoft Research)
- Upscale real workload for enabling faithful systems experimentation under varying loads
- Exploring novel approaches to faithfully increase the load of cloud workloads
- Performance evaluation using 3-tier web server system consisting of Mediawiki web server, Memcached and MySQL database

May, 2022 - December, 2022

#### Capacity Reservation in Cloud System

- Mentors: *Luke Marshall, Beibin Li* and *Ishai Menache* (Cloud Operations Research (CORE) MSR)
- Develop capacity reservation techniques for Azure which maximizes sellable capacity while minimizing SLA violation risk
- Extend existing simulator to analyze different capacity reservation techniques for comparison

May,2021 - August,2021

#### Development of Flight Simulator for Spark Jobs

- Mentors: Abhishek Roy and Joyce Cahoon (Gray Systems Lab (GSL), Microsoft)
- Create realistic benchmark for Spark Workloads from query traces
- Generate synthetic representative datasets for the benchmark

2018 - 2020

#### ■ Downscale Workloads from Cloud Infrastructure and Large Datacenters

- Mentors: *Timothy Zhu* and *Bhuvan Urgaonkar* (The Pennsylvania State University), *Siddhartha Sen* (Microsoft Research)
- Downscale cloud workload while preserving important characteristics to facilitate realistic systems research and industry prototyping
- Proposed novel techniques for realistically downscaling workloads that preserve important characteristics such as arrival process and performance
- For performance evaluation, implemented a 3- tier web server system consisting of Elgg web server, Memcached and MySQL database using Docker containers on Linux
- For real world case study, implemented autoscaler on Wikimedia application with MySQL database
- Used statistical methods (e.g. energy distance) for data analysis

# Professional Experience

May, 2022 - August,2022

**Research Intern** at Cloud Operations Research (CORE), Microsoft Research.

May, 2021 - August,2021

**Research Intern** at Gray Systems Lab (GSL), Microsoft.

August, 2018 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant and Graduate Teaching Assistant at The Pennsylvania State University.

October, 2017 - July, 2018

**Junior Software Engineer** at Reve Systems.

### **Awards**

2021	Registration Grant, Sigmetrics 2021	
2020	Student Grant, USENIX Symposium on Operating Systems Design and Implementation (OSDI)	
2019, 2018	Student Travel Grant, ACM Symposium on Cloud Computing (SoCC)	
2018	Technical Scholarship, Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology	
2012	Higher Secondary Certificate Scholarship, Dhaka Education Board, Bangladesh	
2009	Junior Scholarship, Dhaka Education Board, Bangladesh	

# **Skills**

Programming Languages	Java, Python, C++, Scala, C, R, Scheme, Assembly (Intel 8086)
Analysis Tools	MATLAB, Weka
Databases	Oracle, MySQL, SQLite
Frameworks	Apache Spark, Android, Spring-Boot, JPA, JSP, Scikit-Learn, Bootstrap

Technologies AWS Services and SDK, Azure Services and CLI, Docker, Git

## References

#### Timothy Zhu

Assistant Professor, Department of Computer Science and Engineering

The Pennsylvania State University

timothyz@cse.psu.edu

#### Siddhartha Sen

Principal Researcher Microsoft Research in New York City

✓ sidsen@microsoft.com

#### Bhuvan Urgaonkar

Professor, Department of Computer Science and Engineering

The Pennsylvania State University

buu1@psu.edu